Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
This vast amount of junk floating in space,
space debris, is a very serious threat.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
宇宙に浮かぶ たくさんのゴミ
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
2076年―
This is a story of 2076, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
作業員[さぎょういん]:laborer/labourer/blue-collar worker, 船体[せんたい]:hull, 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment, 機構[きこう]:mechanism/organization/organisation, システム:system, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
（作業員１）
船体分離機構のシステムチェック
Hull separation mechanism
system check.
連結[れんけつ]:concatenation/coupling/connection, 動力[どうりょく]:power/motive power|three-phase electricity, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking
連結部 動力連絡部 誘導制御部
Couplers, power transmission,
guidance and control.
共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, アビオニクス:avionics, 連携[れんけい]:cooperation/coordination/link, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
共にアビオニクスとの連携確認
Connection of all systems
to avionics confirmed.
作業員[さぎょういん]:laborer/labourer/blue-collar worker, 重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination, 機構[きこう]:mechanism/organization/organisation, 可動[かどう]:mobile/moveable
（作業員２）プライマリーハルの
重心位置調整機構の可動部…
Moving elements of gravity
adjustment mechanism...
すっげえ:incredible/unbelievable
（ハチマキ）すっげえ！
Awesome! This baby's fresh
off the assembly line!
新造[しんぞう, しんぞ]:new|unmarried woman of about 20|newly-married woman|, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
ピッカピカの新造船だぜ こりゃあ
It's still in the wrapper!
ビニール:vinyl, 掛かる[かかる]:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang|to come into view||
おっ まだビニール 掛かってるよ
フィー:phi, 剥がす[はがす, へがす]:to tear off/to peel off/to rip off
フィー 剥がしてもいいか？ これ
Fee! Can I rip
this off?!
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
（フィー）好きにしな
Knock yourself out.
よーし:alright/all right/right on
よーし いいねえ これこれ
ハハハハハ…
Oh, yeah! I love this stuff!
うっひゃあ！
I feel like a
captain already!
気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
気分は もう船長！
ダッハハハッ…
He's like a kid who
just got a new toy.
おもちゃ:toy/plaything, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 子供[こども]:child/children, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（タナベ）なんか
おもちゃ買ってもらった子供みたい
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 子供[こども]:child/children
男なんて 一生 子供だよ
Men are kids their
whole lives.
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!, すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
（ハチマキ）うわあ すげえ すげえ
Wow, check this out!
It's got a D5 instead of a D2!
Ｄ２じゃなくて Ｄ５になってるよ
ハハッ ハハハハハ…
Tanabe, you have
a visitor.
お客さん[おきゃくさん]:guest/visitor|customer
（ユーリ）タナベ お客さんだ
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
えっ こんな所にですか？
What, here?
She said that she's been waiting for you to
return to Seven, so I brought her on board.
セブン:seven, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
（ユーリ）君がセブンに戻るのを
ずっと待ってたって言うから
（タナベ）誰だろう
（リュシー）私よ
Who could it be?
Me, that's who!
Lucie?
リュシー
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
大事な話があるの ついてきて
I have something important to talk
to you about. Come with me.
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
誰もいない所がいいわ
Someplace where
we can be alone.
ああっ…
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
Phase 14
Turning Point
えっ？
You like him,
don't you?
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
だから 好きなんでしょ？ 彼のこと
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
（タナベ）あっ う… うん 多分
Yeah... I think.
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
寝たの？
Have you slept
with him?
（タナベ）えっ？ そんな…
Of course not!
何も…
キスは しそうになったけど
We haven't done anything...
Well, we did
almost kiss, though...
Ah.
そう
At first, I thought he was just
some irresponsible guy...
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, ちゃらんぽらん:blithe/devil-may-care/speaking off-hand
最初は ちゃらんぽらんな人だと
思ったんだけど
But when he chews me out over something,
it's really because he has pride in his job.
きつい:intense/severe|determined
でも 私にきつく言うのって―
プライド:pride, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
プライド持って
仕事してるからなんだよね
はあ？
And he has a
soft side, too...
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
（タナベ）それにね
優しいところもあるんだよ
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising, つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
ちゃんと私ができるようになるまで
練習つきあってくれるし―
When I'm practicing, he stays with me
until I can do it properly on my own.
正義感[せいぎかん]:sense of justice, 子供[こども]:child/children, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
正義感 強いし
本当は 子供好きだし
And he's got a strong sense of justice,
and he likes kids a lot, too.
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと 何言ってるの？
Uh... What are you
talking about?
What I'm saying is, we almost kissed.
Hachimaki-senpai and me.
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, ハチマキ:headband, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
だからキスしそうになったって
ハチマキ先輩と
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
（リュシー）
えっ！ おむつ男と！？
With Diaper Man?!
（作業員）うん？
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 言い方[いいかた]:way of talking/speaking style
やめてよ そんな言い方
Come on, stop calling him that!
All astronauts wear diapers.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
宇宙飛行士なら
誰でも おむつ はくんだから
I'm dense about these things,
so I never realized how I felt.
鈍い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, 鈍い[にぶい, のろい]:dull (e.g. a knife)|thickheaded|dull (sound, color, etc.)||, 全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
私 鈍いから
全然 自分の気持ちに気づかなくて
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
リュシーのほうが
先に分かってたよね
You noticed it first,
didn't you, Lucie?
I wonder when I started feeling
this way about him? I always...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
私 いつから
先輩を好きになっていたんだろう
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
ずっと… あっ ごめん 私ばっかり
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm doing all the talking.
ああっ…
You wanted to talk about
something, right, Lucie?
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（タナベ）
リュシー 話あるんだよね？
…で 何？ 話って
So, what is it?
（リュシー）ああ…
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
頑張れ！
（タナベ）えっ あの… 話は？
Hang in there!
Um, with what?
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
（リュシー）頑張れ！
Hang in there!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
頑張れ！ タナベ
Hang in there, Tanabe!
えっ… うん
Listen to this! Toy Box 2 can
make it to the moon on its own, and can even land
on the surface!
（ハチマキ）
なあ この ToyBox(トイボックス)２は―
単独[たんどく]:sole/single|independence, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 着陸[ちゃくりく]:landing/alighting/touch down
月まで単独で行けて
しかも月着陸まで できるんだぜ
The engine's a
laser-ignition model,
エンジン:engine, レーザー:laser/Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation, レーザー:leather, 着火[ちゃっか]:ignited/kindled/catching (fire), 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|
エンジンは
レーザー着火式だし―
タンク:tank (of liquid), 増設[ぞうせつ]:extension/expansion/adding (equipment, facilities, etc.), 一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer), 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
タンクを増設すれば
一気に火星だって行けるかもな
...and if we added extra tanks, it might
even be able to go all the way to Mars!
Say, Hachi.
（チェンシン）なあ ハチ
（ハチマキ）あ？
How's Tanabe-san been lately?
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now
（チェンシン）
タナベさん 最近どうしてる？
あ？
She's been giving me the cold shoulder ever
since the Space Defense Front incident.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident, そっけない:cold/short/curt
（チェンシン）
この間の 宇宙防衛戦線の事件から
そっけないんだよな
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat, 誘う[さそう, いざなう]:to invite/to ask|to tempt, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave
さっき食事に誘ったんだけど
断られたし… 何か聞いてる？
I asked her out to dinner a while ago,
but she turned me down.
Has she said anything
to you?
いや 別に… あっ
No, not really.
おあっ！
（チェンシン）何？
What?
やべえ:dangerous/risky, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
（ハチマキ）やべえ 忘れてた…
Oh, crap! I totally
forgot about that!
くーっ…
（課長）あ～あ ああ…
やっぱり:too/also|still, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
（ハチマキ）やっぱり
あそこまで行った以上―
We went that far, so...
So I have to do
this right.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
ちゃんとしないと いかんよなあ
As the man...
男として
I've gotta do it right...
いかん… いかんなあ
ああ…
Senpai, we're supposed to mix this in
with the ferret feed, right?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, フェレット:ferret (Mustela putorius furo), 餌[えさ, え]:(animal) feed/fodder|bait
（タナベ）
先輩 フェレットの餌って―
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
これと一緒で いいんでしたよね？
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（ハチマキ）ちゃんと最後まで…
See it through all the way. To the bitter end.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩？
Senpai!
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ハチマキ）
あっ ああ 悪い 聞いてなかった
Oh. I'm sorry, I wasn't listening.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
地球ボケですか？ 先輩
Do you have Earth-lag?
あっ…
Your mom's pork cutlets were
delicious, and the sea was pretty.
お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, トンカツ:tonkatsu/breaded pork cutlet, おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive
（タナベ）お母さんのトンカツ
おいしかったし―
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, きれい:pretty/lovely|clean
海もきれいだったし―
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 恋しい[こいしい]:yearned for/longed for/missed, 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
地球が恋しくなっても
無理ないですよね
It's not surprising that
you miss the Earth.
タナベ
（タナベ）はい？
Tanabe...
Yes?
Um... Once we're off, do you want
to go grab something to eat?
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 飯[めし]:cooked rice|meal|one's livelihood, 飯[まんま, まま]:cooked rice
（ハチマキ）
その… 仕事 終わったら
飯でも行かねえか？
フィー:phi, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（タナベ）いいですよ
フィーさんたちが帰ってきたら
Sure, we can go once Fee-san and Yuri get back.
（ハチマキ）違(ちげ)えよ！
That's not
what I meant!
あっ…
あー
Um, I... I meant
just you and me.
いや その… 俺と お前だけで
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（タナベ）あっ…
（ハチマキ）駄目か？
You don't want to?
（タナベ）フッ…
I've been meaning to
tell you something...
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
私 ずっと先輩に…
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 注目[ちゅうもく]:notice/attention/observation
（ラビィ）全員 注目！
Listen up, everyone! The following
is an order from the manager.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 命令を伝える[めいれいをつたえる]:to pass on an order/to pass the word
これより 係長命令を伝える
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
（ハチマキ）ああっ？
（タナベ）係長命令？
Orders from
the manager?
Orders from the
assistant manager.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
（エーデル）係長補佐命令
（ラビィ）あう…
Um, what is it?
（タナベ）あの… 何か？
（ラビィ）うん
Effective today, I am hereby banning office
dating here in Second Division, Debris Section!
本日[ほんじつ]:today, 我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
本日より
我が 第２事業部デブリ課は―
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
社内恋愛を禁止する！
（タナベ･ハチマキ）ええっ！？
ああっ…
何か言った？
Did you say something?
It's less than 100 days until the
Von Braun's
outfitting is to be completed.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（ドルフ）
フォン･ブラウン号の―
艤装[ぎそう]:fitting-out of a ship/rigging/ship's outfit, 完了[かんりょう]:completion/conclusion|perfect (tense, form, aspect), 完了[ワンラ]:end/completion, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
艤装(ぎそう)完了まで
100日を切っているというのに―
What do you mean, the shipping schedule for
the tandem mirror engine hasn't been fixed yet?
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 搬入[はんにゅう]:taking in/bringing in (esp. heavy objects, artwork, furniture)/carrying in, スケジュール:schedule
タンデムミラーエンジンの
搬入スケジュールが―
フィックス:fix, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, どういう:somehow/how/in what way
フィックスしていないのは
どういうことだ？
It looks like the load was
too much for Claire.
荷[に]:load/baggage|burden, 荷[か]:counter for loads (that can be carried on one's shoulders), 重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||
（ゲイハート）クレア君には
荷が重かったようですな
Following through on the matter
was your job as her superior.
フォロー:follow, 上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 役目[やくめ]:duty/role/function
フォローするのは
上司の君の役目だろ
指導[しどう]:leadership/guidance|shido (disciplinary action for a minor infringement of the rules of judo), 山々[やまやま]:(many) mountains|very much (esp. wanting to do something one cannot)/greatly, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless
指導したいのは山々ですが
彼女も いろいろと忙しそうで
I'd like nothing better than
to offer her some guidance,
...but she seems to be rather
busy with other things.
（ドルフ）うん？
She's over at the OSA
right now.
保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
今 保安庁に行ってます
I see it was a mistake to let her oversee the
Orbital Security Operating Audit, as well.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保全[ほぜん]:preservation/integrity/conservation, 業務[ぎょうむ]:business/affairs/duties, 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, 誤り[あやまり]:error/mistake/slip
軌道保全業務の監査まで任せたのは
誤りでしたね
Her mistakes have been
awfully conspicuous lately, too.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 目立つ[めだつ]:to be conspicuous/to stand out
最近 ミスも目立ちますしね 彼女
Perhaps you should assign
someone else to oversee it.
担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.), 替える[かえる]:to replace|to exchange|to substitute
別の人間に担当を替えるべきでは？
We'll accept it this time, but be more
careful from now on, all right?
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 受け取る[うけとる]:to receive/to get|to take
（職員）
今回は これで受け取りますが―
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
次回は気をつけてください
（クレア）はい すいません
I will. I'm terribly sorry.
別表[べっぴょう]:annexed (statistical) table, いつごろ:about when/how soon
（職員）それと別表のほうは
いつごろになりますか？
When can we expect
the attached forms?
Sometime next week.
来週[らいしゅう]:next week
来週中には
今週[こんしゅう]:this week, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（職員）今週中でお願いします
Make it before the end of this week.
I'm going on vacation next week.
来週[らいしゅう]:next week, 休暇[きゅうか]:holiday/day off/furlough, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
来週は
私 休暇を取っていますので
あっ 分かりました
I'll do that. You need Form 35, right?
書式[しょしき]:blank form/format, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., よろしい:good/OK/all right
書式は 35号で
よろしいんですね？
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（職員）はい よろしく
Yep, that's the one.
あっ
（クレア）待って
Wait!
（ハキム）うん？ 君は…
And you are?
Could you please tell me?
How is Temara Poitier doing?
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
教えてもらえませんか？
テマラ･ポワチエは
今 どうしているのか？
Tanabe-kun, you know about Third Division, right?
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ラビィ）タナベ君
第３事業部って分かるよね
事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ハチマキ）月の事業部だろ？
They're our
lunar division, right?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, お嬢[おじょう]:(someone else's) daughter
うん そこの
事業部長のお嬢さん―
Right. The daughter of their division manager
works for Technora as a receptionist.
受付嬢[うけつけじょう]:receptionist/reception woman, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 妊娠[にんしん]:conception/pregnancy
テクノーラで受付嬢やってんだけど
この間 妊娠してな
She got pregnant recently.
めでたい:happy/auspicious|naive
おめでたいじゃないですか
Isn't that wonderful news?
めでたい:happy/auspicious|naive
めでたくない！
No, it's not!
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
（ハチマキ）
親父(おやじ)が誰か 分からないとか？
What, they don't know
who the father is?
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 研究員[けんきゅういん]:researcher/lab worker
（ラビィ）いや
同じ第３事業部の研究員なんだよ
No, he's a scientist who also
works for Third Division.
Ah, an office romance.
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion
社内恋愛かあ
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, カンカン:can-can, カンカン:extreme anger/fury/rage
（ラビィ）
事業部長は カンカンだそうだ
They say the division manager
is raging mad.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
今 第３事業部は
大変なことになっている
All of Third Division is
in turmoil right now!
なんでだよ
How come?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 身分[みぶん]:social position/social status, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
事業部長の娘と平だぞ
身分が違い過ぎる
It's the manager's daughter and
a rank-and-file employee!
Their social standings
are too different!
身分[みぶん]:social position/social status
何ですか？ 身分って
What do social standings
have to do with it?
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
あるんだよ 会社には
Inside a company,
it matters plenty.
So, what's happened
to the two kids?
（課長）…で その２人
どうなっちゃったの？
火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 採掘[さいくつ]:mining, 工場[こうじょう, こうば]:factory/plant/mill, 出向[しゅっこう]:secondment/temporary transfer|proceeding, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
（ラビィ）
男のほうは 火星の採掘工場に
出向が決まりました
The boy's been reassigned
to a mining plant on Mars.
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
おかしいですよ！ そんなの
They can't do that! It's not right!
They can't break up two people
who love each other!
愛し合う[あいしあう]:to love one another/to be affectionate towards each other|to have sex, 引き裂く[ひきさく]:to tear up/to tear off|to separate (e.g. a couple), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
愛し合ってる２人を
引き裂くなんて
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
愛の前には
平も部長もないと思います！
There's no such thing as labor or
management where love is concerned!
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
だから 会社にはあるんだって
Look, in a company,
there are!
Now that you mention it, that Kuroda boy who
transferred here recently asked to come here...
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 異動[いどう]:change (personnel)/transfer/reshuffle, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
（課長）そういや
この間 異動してきたクロダ君
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 部署[ぶしょ]:one's post/one's station/department, いたたまれる:to collect/to gather/to save, いたたまれる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
別れた彼女が同じ部署で
いたたまれなくなって―
...because he couldn't stand working in the
same department as his ex-girlfriend.
異動[いどう]:change (personnel)/transfer/reshuffle, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
異動させてもらったって
言ってたなあ
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion
（ラビィ）
でしょう？ 社内恋愛は―
See what I mean?
Office romances
cause all sorts of trouble.
いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), ややこしい:puzzling/tangled/complicated
いろいろ ややこしいことに
なりがちなんですよ
だからって…
Still, that doesn't
mean you...
Yeah, it makes you feel sorry
for them, doesn't it?
かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
うん かわいそうだよねえ
Chief, it wasn't just the regular
employee who was demoted.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 左遷[させん]:demotion/relegation/reduction in rank, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee
（ラビィ）課長 左遷の話
平だけじゃないんですよ
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（課長）まさか！
（ラビィ）はい
They didn't!
They did! They shipped his
supervisor off to Mars, too.
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 仲良く[なかよく]:on good terms with/on cordial terms with|to make friends with, 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 行き[ゆき, いき]:bound for ...|going (to)
上司も仲良く 火星行きです
定年[ていねん]:retirement age|years of service in a military rank before eligibility for promotion, 間際[まぎわ]:on the verge of/just before/on the point of, 容赦[ようしゃ]:pardon/forgiveness|leniency
定年間際でも容赦なく
He was on the verge of retirement,
but that didn't stop them.
ひょえーっ！
Officially, it's for an expansion of
our Mars environmental business.
表向き[おもてむき]:outward appearance/ostensible/public, 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, 事業[じぎょう, ことわざ]:project/enterprise|act, 拡大[かくだい]:magnification/enlargement/expansion, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
表向きは 火星環境事業拡大って
ことになってますが
休む[やすむ]:to be absent|to rest|to go to bed|, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
（課長）ああ…
僕らが休んでる間にそんなことに
I can't believe something like that happened
while we were on vacation...
（タナベ･ハチマキ）ああ…
しばらく:little while/short while|a while, 社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
（課長）じゃあ しばらくは
社内恋愛禁止ってことで
Anyway, office romances are
banned for the time being.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（タナベ･ハチマキ）ええっ！？
（課長）よろしくね
All right?
えっ でも…
Aw, but...
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
課長命令だぞ タナベ君
That's an order from the
section chief, Tanabe-kun.
From the assistant
section chief.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
課長補佐命令
Please understand, Ai-chan.
I'm going to be retiring soon.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 定年[ていねん]:retirement age|years of service in a military rank before eligibility for promotion
（課長）頼むよ 愛(あい)ちゃん
僕 もうすぐ 定年だしさ
Please! Okay?
ねっ ねっ
ハチ！ お前もだぞ
（ハチマキ）なんでだよ
Hachi! That goes
for you, too!
Why are you
telling me?
You have a history of it,
remember?
前科[ぜんか]:previous conviction/criminal record/previous offense
前科があるだろ？
ああっ？
You used to go out with that Claire girl
over in Control Section, right?
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 嬢[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
ハッちゃん 管制課のクレア嬢と
つきあってたんでしょ？
な… なんで！？
H-How did you
know that?!
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
この間 愛ちゃんが言ってた
（タナベ）えっ？
Ai-chan mentioned it
a while ago.
そんなこと言ってるから
クレアさんにもフラれるんですよ！
Claire-san dumped you because
you say mean things like that!
ああっ
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
ハッちゃん
好きな人 いるのかい？
Ha-chan, is there anyone
that you're interested in?
You aren't seeing someone
already, are you?
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
実は もうつきあってる人が
いるんじゃないだろうな
N-No, there isn't! I'm not seeing anybody,
and I'm not interested in anybody!
い… いねえよ！
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
つきあってる女も好きな女も
Technora women might be real go-getters,
but they've all got ugly personalities!
成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
成績は いいかもしんねえけど―
性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition, ばっか:only/merely|approximately, じゃん:isn't it
性格ブスばっかじゃん
テクノーラの女って
ぎっ…
あっ ああ…
（タナベ）んん…
（ラビィ）では そういうことで
That's that, then.
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
（ハチマキ）お… おーい
H-Hey!
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（課長）
じゃあ みんな よろしくね
Well, thanks for your
understanding, everyone!
（ハチマキ）俺は まだ…
I still haven't...
agreed to anything.
承知[しょうち]:knowledge|consent|forgiving
承知したわけじゃ…
弱る[よわる]:to weaken/to be troubled/to be downcast, そりゃ:very/extremely|that is, 急ぎ[いそぎ]:haste/hurry/expedition
（キース）
弱ったなあ そりゃ また急ぎだな
That's a tall order... And it's a big rush, too.
You've got that test flight
to the moon tomorrow, right?
あした:morning, あした:tomorrow|near future, テスト:test, 飛行[ひこう]:aviation/flight|to fly, 飛行[ひぎょう]:flying without hindrance
あした
月までのテスト飛行だったよな
All right, I'll try to get everything
together before then.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use, そろえる:to collect/to gather|to arrange
しかたない それまでには
なんとか そろえとくよ
Sorry about that. I owe you one.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 恩に着る[おんにきる]:to feel oneself indebted to
（ユーリ）悪いな 恩に着るよ
（キース）おっ おう
それじゃあ 19時にな
Sure. I'll see you at 1900 hours, then.
ああ
Sure.
Yuri, did something happen
down on Earth?
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe
（フィー）
ユーリ 地球で何かあった？
You think I've changed?
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ユーリ）人が変わったみたい？
うん
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come, エンジニア:engineer, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
（ユーリ）未来のエンジニアがね
壊してくれたんだ
A future engineer broke
something for me.
（フィー）うん？
過去[かこ]:the past|a past (i.e. a personal history one would prefer remained secret)|past (tense)|, こだわる:to fuss over/to be particular about|to be obsessive about
（ユーリ）過去にこだわる自分を
The part of me that couldn't
let go of the past.
フフッ…
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
（フィー）ふーん
Temara Poitier is being held under
extremely humane conditions.
極めて[きわめて]:exceedingly/extremely/decisively, 人道的[じんどうてき]:humane, 保護[ほご, ほうご]:care/protection/shelter
（ハキム）テマラ･ポワチエは
極めて人道的に保護されています
However, I'm told that all the research data
for his spacesuit was confiscated.
ただし:but/however/provided that, 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 没収[ぼっしゅう]:forfeiture/seizure/confiscation
ただし 宇宙服の研究資料は
全て 没収されたようですが
Because the technology could be applied
towards weapons, I suppose.
兵器[へいき]:arms/weapons/ordnance, 転用[てんよう]:diversion/putting something to another use, 可能[かのう]:potential/possible/practicable, 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art
兵器に転用可能な技術ですものね
Why are you standing
up for him?
肩入れ[かたいれ]:support/backing/patronage, 同情[どうじょう]:sympathy/compassion/feeling pity for
なぜ彼に肩入れを？ 同情ですか？
Is it sympathy? Or out of
opposition to INTO?
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 反発[はんぱつ]:opposition|rebounding|rally (e.g. in stock prices)
それとも連合への反発？
I...
私…
（ハキム）うん？
貴族[きぞく]:noble/aristocrat
私 貴族には なれないな
I suppose I'll never be
one of the nobility...
（ハキム）うん？
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
（ハチマキ）何 怒ってんだよ
What are you
mad about?
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
怒ってません
I'm not mad!
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
怒ってるだろ？
Yes, you are! I said that because...
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
さっきのはだな うっ…
社内恋愛禁止とか―
Because of the ban
on office romances.
おかしな:ridiculous/odd
おかしなこと言いだすから
That's what you get
for blabbing!
いいんじゃないですか？
It's better this way, isn't it? Now you don't
have to make do with what's on hand.
我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance, 手近[てぢか, てじか]:near/close by|familiar, 済ます[すます]:to finish|to settle|to get along (without something)
我慢して
手近で済ますことないですよ
嫌み[いやみ]:disagreeableness/disagreeability/gaudiness
（ハチマキ）嫌み言うなよ
C'mon, don't be
so sarcastic!
性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
性格ブスですから
I can't help it, I have
an ugly personality.
売り言葉[うりことば]:inflammatory words, 買い言葉[かいことば]:tit for tat
だから あれは
売り言葉に買い言葉っていうか
Look, that was me
responding in kind!
つい…
I couldn't help it.
It's prohibited!
禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
禁止です！
（ハチマキ）えっ？
Going any farther
is now prohibited.
立ち入り禁止[たちいりきんし]:No Entry/No Trespassing|off-limits, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
立ち入り禁止ですよ これ以上は
（ハチマキ）あっ…
ああ…
（リュシー）ウフッ ウフフッ…
読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
チェンシンさん
何 読んでるんですか？
Cheng-Shin-san!
What's that you're reading?
The documentation on the Von Braun.
It's going to Jupiter.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet)
フォン･ブラウン号の資料
木星へ行く…
They're going to start taking
crew applications soon.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 乗員[じょういん]:crew, 募集[ぼしゅう]:recruiting|raising|flotation (shares, loans, etc.), 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
そろそろ
乗員の募集が始まるからね
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
乗るんですか？
You're joining
the crew?!
テスト:test, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
テストは受けてみるつもり
I plan to take
the test.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（リュシー）だって木星ですよ
７年間 帰ってこられないんですよ
This is Jupiter we're talking about!
You won't come back for seven years!
（チェンシン）そうだね
I suppose not...
How can you
say it like that?
（リュシー）そうだねって…
Calling Seven,
this is DS-12.
セブン:seven, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（フィー）セブンへ こちらDS-12
We are go for taking free. Main umbilical, separate.
フリー:free (of restraint, controls, etc.), 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
テーキング フリー ゴー 確認
メイン:main/principal part, セパレート:separate
メイン アンビリカル セパレート
Separation complete. You copy?
セパレート:separate, コンプリート:complete, コピー:copy/photocopy
（クレア）セパレート
コンプリート ユー コピー？
コピー:copy/photocopy, フリー:free (of restraint, controls, etc.)
（フィー）
アイ コピー テイキング フリー
I copy. Taking free.
あっ… あの２人 何かあったの？
DS-12, this is Seven. Establishing datalink via Navstar.
Did something happen
between those two?
あの２人？
What two?
ハチとタナベ君だよ
Hachi and Tanabe-kun.
Datalink confirmed.
Things seem to be awfully chilly between those two.
冷たい[つめたい, つべたい]:cold (to the touch)/chilly|coldhearted, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence
すっごく冷たい空気がさ
We will be making orbital plane change
using ME to reach transfer orbit,
ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
いつものケンカでしょ？
気にすることないですよ
It's just one of their usual fights.
It's nothing to worry about.
Still...
...so we will separate using OMS
until we reach changeover point.
けど…
なーんか
いつもと違うっていうかさ
It seems a little different
from their usual ones.
Please verify vector
and window datalink.
（ハチマキ）ん…
DS-12, this is Seven. Vector and window
navigation data matrix downlink complete.
ん…
ナビゲーション:navigation, データ:data/datum, マトリックス:matrix
（クレア）ナビゲーション
データマトリックスに―
ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down, リンク:link/directory entry, コンプリート:complete
ダウンリンク コンプリート
♪～
Are we there yet?
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
（ラビィ）着いたの？
ラグランジュアン
We're at Lagrange One, running
a translink test with the Fishbones.
フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, トランス:(power) transformer, リンク:link/directory entry, テスト:test
フィッシュボーンの
トランスリンク テスト中
Oh, really? I guess I'll go
back to sleep, then.
ひと眠り[ひとねむり]:(usu. in positive sentences) (a) sleep/(a) nap|first sleep of silkworms
そっか もうひと眠りしよっかなあ
なあ タナベ
Say, Tanabe...
About Apollo Park... I said I'd take you there,
remember? Once we reach the moon, we...
アポロ:Apollo program/Project Apollo, 公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 連れていく[つれていく, つれてゆく]:to take someone (to some place)/to take someone along/to lead someone away
アポロ公園さ
連れていくって言ったろ？
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||
月に着いたら…
（タナベ）結構です
No thanks. Why don't you go by yourself
and try to score with some girls, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, ナンパ:seducer/smooth talker/ladies' man
先輩一人で行って
ナンパでもしたらどうですか？
You never let things go,
do you?
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, しつこい:insistent/obstinate|too rich (taste, etc.), 性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
（ハチマキ）
お前 結構 しつこい性格してんな
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）
何でも忘れちゃう先輩よりマシです
Better that than forgetting
everything like you do.
（ハチマキ）何がだよ
Forget what?
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
（タナベ）地球で 私に
しようとしたこと忘れてるでしょ？
You don't remember what you tried
to do to me on Earth, do you?
（ハチマキ）
バ… バカ！ んなこと…
M-Moron! Don't bring up that crap here!
（タナベ）
そんなことって… 何ですか！
"That crap"? What do you mean, "That crap"?!
放る[ほうる, ほる]:to throw|to throw away|to neglect, 放る[ひる]:to expel (from the body)/to excrete/to defecate, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
もういいです
放っといてください！
Fine, just forget
about it.
放る[ほうる, ほる]:to throw|to throw away|to neglect, 放る[ひる]:to expel (from the body)/to excrete/to defecate, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
もういいです
放っといてください！
ん！？
トランス:(power) transformer, リンク:link/directory entry, テスト:test, 中止[ちゅうし]:suspension/stoppage/discontinuance
２人とも
トランスリンクテストは中止だ
Abort the translink test.
A meteoroid
is coming at us along our trajectory.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid
軌道方向から小惑星が来てる
I copy. C'mon, Tanabe,
we're heading back.
コピー:copy/photocopy, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（ハチマキ）
アイ コピー タナベ 戻るぞ
（タナベ）分かってますよ
I know that! I can hear Fee-san's
transmissions over here, too, you know!
フィー:phi, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
私にも フィーさんの通信
聞こえてるんですから
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, つっかかる:to charge/to lunge|to flare up (at someone)
（ハチマキ）ただの確認だろ？
そんな つっかかんなよ
I was just getting confirmation, damn it!
Don't bite my head off!
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
（タナベ）
どうせ 性格ブスですから！
- Please come in.
I can't help it. I have an ugly personality.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
（タナベ）
どうせ 性格ブスですから！
（ニン）
ＤＳ-12 ＤＳ-12
- DS-12! DS-12, please respond!
（ニン）
ＤＳ-12 ＤＳ-12
（ハチマキ）お前なあ
Would you give it a rest?!
応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
応答 願います
あっ
DS-12, do you read? Come in, DS-12.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（ニン）
DS-12 聞こえますか？ DS-12
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
こちら DS-12 聞こえますが
This is DS-12. We read you.
何？
What's going on?
つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
よかった つながった
Thank goodness we got through!
Who's in charge over there?
責任者[せきにんしゃ]:person in charge (including a supervisory role for other staff)/person responsible for .../responsible party, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
責任者の方は？
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ラビィ）
私がテクノーラ社 第２事業部―
I'm Technora's Second Division, Debris Section
(Assistant) Manager, Arvind Lavie.
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 係長[かかりちょう]:chief clerk, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
デブリ課 係長… 補佐
アルヴィンド･ラビィだ
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), いちばん:number one/first|best, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful
この船では いちばん偉い
I'm the highest ranking
person aboard this ship.
Please, Mr. Manager.
You've got to save our dream.
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 係長[かかりちょう]:chief clerk, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ニン）お願いします 係長さん
私たちの夢を救ってください
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 係長[かかりちょう]:chief clerk, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ニン）お願いします 係長さん
私たちの夢を救ってください
（ラビィ）えっ？
Our experiment module is along
the meteoroid's path.
小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid, 進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school)
（ニン）小惑星の進路に―
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 実験[じっけん]:experiment, モジュール:module
私たちの
実験モジュールがあるんです
It'll only be two more days before
our experiments produce results.
実験[じっけん]:experiment, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, たった:only/merely/but
実験の結果が出るまで
あと たった２日なのに
（フィー）ああっ？
We beg of you. Is there anything
you can do to save our module?
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
お願いです あなた方の力で―
モジュール:module, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, いただける:to be able to receive/to be able to take|to be able to eat
なんとか モジュールを
助けていただけないでしょうか？
これって…
Wait, that's...
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 無人[むじん, ぶにん]:lack of help|unmanned/uninhabited, モジュール:module
我が社の
無人モジュールじゃないか
That's one of our company's
unmanned modules.
申す[もうす]:to say/to be called|to do, 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
あっ はい 申し遅れました
Yes, sir. I'm sorry, I forgot to introduce myself.
My name is Ning Mantegna. I'm a scientist with
Technora's Third Division, Research Section.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
私は テクノーラ社
第３事業部 研究課―
ニン･マンテーニャと言います
Mantegna? Oh, pregnancy boy!
マンテーニャ？
妊娠[にんしん]:conception/pregnancy
あっ！ 妊娠男
妊娠？
Pregnancy boy?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, お嬢[おじょう]:(someone else's) daughter, 妊娠[にんしん]:conception/pregnancy, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
（ラビィ）ほら 事業部長の
お嬢さんを妊娠させたって
You know, the guy who knocked up
the daughter of Third Division's manager!
あっ ああ…
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 責任を取る[せきにんをとる]:to take responsibility
（研究課長）気にするな
お前は責任を取るって言ってるんだ
Don't worry about it. You said you'd
do the right thing, didn't you?
Yeah, yeah! It's that stupid old man's fault
for not giving you two his blessing!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, そうそう:so long/so often|oh, yes!, そうそう:funeral/burial rites|attendance at a funeral, 仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 認める[したためる]:to write up, 認める[みとめる]:to recognize|to deem|to approve||, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（社員１）そうそう
２人の仲を認めないバカ親父が悪い
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員２）そうだ
（社員３）そうだよ
He's right!
Yeah!
（研究課長）なっ？
Right?
Please listen to me.
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
聞いてください
We've spent five years researching
catch connective tissue...
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, コンセプト:concept/general idea/notion, 装甲[そうこう]:armoring/armouring/armor, 素材[そざい]:raw materials/subject matter, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
私たちは 新しいコンセプトの
装甲素材を作るため―
...to create a new concept
in armor material.
キャッチ:catch/catching/obtaining (e.g. information), 結合[けつごう]:combination/union|bond, 組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
キャッチ結合組織の開発に
丸５年もかけてきたんです
But we're going to be split up
and transferred next week.
来週[らいしゅう]:next week, バラバラ:scattered/disperse/loose, 異動[いどう]:change (personnel)/transfer/reshuffle
しかし 来週には
バラバラに異動させられる
This is our
last chance!
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, チャンス:chance/opportunity
これが最後のチャンスなんです
事情[じじょう]:circumstances/consideration/conditions
（ラビィ）いや まあ
事情はよく知ってるけど
Well, I'm fully aware of your
circumstances, but...
狭い[せまい]:narrow/confined/small, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
フンッ 心の狭い親父だな
That guy is one
narrow-minded dad.
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（ニン）お願いします
Please help! You're the only ones
anywhere near here!
付近[ふきん]:neighbourhood/neighborhood|approaching
その付近には
あなたたちしかいないんです
Don't let our last dream die. Please.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 何とぞ[なにとぞ, なにそつ]:please/kindly|by all means
私たちの最後の夢を 何とぞ
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩？
Senpai?
ハチマキ:headband
待て ハチマキ
Hold it, Hachimaki!
インパクト:impact, ドライバー:driver (of a vehicle)
（ハチマキ）
インパクトドライバーを使えば―
We might be able to do something for them
if we use our impact drivers.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
なんとかできるかもしれねえ
小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.), 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
（ラビィ）そうじゃない
小惑星を壊すのは禁止だ
That's not what I mean!
Destroying meteoroids is prohibited!
禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
（ハチマキ）また禁止かよ！
You're prohibiting
this, too?!
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 免許[めんきょ]:license/permit/licence, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
お前は デブリ回収免許しか
持ってないだろ？
You only have a license to
collect debris, remember?
Meteoroids are natural bodies,
not debris!
小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid, 自然[しぜん]:nature|natural|naturally, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, デブリ:debris
小惑星は 自然物で
デブリじゃないんだ！
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
そんなの関係あるか！
What's that got to do
with anything?!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, 保存[ほぞん]:preservation/conservation|saving (e.g. to disk), 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|
あるんだよ
宇宙環境保存法ってのがあってな
Everything! There's a little thing called
the Space Environmental Protection Act!
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, 違反[いはん]:violation/offense/offence, 違反[いへん]:breaking (a contract, promise, etc.), 犯罪者[はんざいしゃ]:criminal/culprit
連合法に違反すれば犯罪者だぞ
If you break INTO law,
you'll be a criminal!
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 問う[とう]:to ask|to charge (e.g. with a crime)|without regard to|
上司の私も責任を問われる
I'm your superior, so I'll be held responsible!
I won't be able to support my children!
養育費[よういくひ]:child-rearing expenses/child-support payments (following divorce), 払う[はらう]:to pay (e.g. money, bill)|to brush off|to drive away (e.g. one's competitors)||
養育費だって払えなくなるんだ
（ハチマキ）だったら―
Which means that if I move the module,
there's no problem, right?!
モジュール:module, 動かす[うごかす]:to move|to inspire|to change||, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
モジュールのほうを動かせば
問題ないだろ？
えっ？ ああ… それなら…
Um. Well, I guess...
Would that work?
いいのかな？
いいんじゃない？
Sure, why not?
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
ありがとう 第２事業部の人
Thanks, Second Division.
Don't sweat it. I'm doing this 'cause I want to.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
（ハチマキ）気にすんな
俺は やりたいからやってんだ
You should also do what you want.
Forget about parents or your company rank.
あんたも やりたいようにやれよ
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
親とか平とか関係なくさ
（ハチマキ）さて…
Okay, now...
A little over three minutes
to collision, huh?
衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict, ちょい:heirship, ちょい:just a minute/short time|somewhat
（ハチマキ）
衝突まで あと３分ちょいか
If I use my return fuel, too,
I should be able to...
機関[からくり]:mechanism|trick|mechanical doll, 機関[きかん]:engine|agency|system, 推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant
機関分の推進剤を使えば なんとか
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 諸君[しょくん]:you (people)|gentlemen/ladies and gentlemen
（ノーマン）
そこまでだ 第２事業部の諸君
That's far enough, men
of the Second Division.
（ハチマキ）何だ？
What the...?
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
（ノーマン）月軌道は
我が 第３事業部の担当だ
We of the Third Division are
in charge of Lunar orbit.
I'll have to ask Second Division
to stay out of this.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 遠慮[えんりょ]:reserve|declining|forethought, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
第２事業部には
遠慮してもらいたいものだな
（ハチマキ）誰だよ？ おい
Who the hell
are you?
Norman Schwimmer,
Division manager
of Third Division.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
第３事業部 部長
ノーマン･シュワイマーだ
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
じ… 事業部長様
Mr. Division Manager, sir!
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
バカ親父か
The dumb daddy, huh?
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
部長 お願いします
この研究だけは最後まで
Manager, please! Let us
complete this experiment!
What do you hope to accomplish
by researching sea cucumbers?
ナマコ:sea cucumber (Holothuroidea spp.), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
ナマコなんて研究してどうする
モジュール:module, 小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
そんなモジュール
小惑星にでも当たって―
It'll be better for the company to let that meteoroid
hit the module and collect the insurance money.
保険金[ほけんきん]:insurance payout/insurance money, せしめる:to cheat someone out of/to wangle|to get, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
保険金をせしめるほうが
会社のためだ
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid
（ニン）それじゃ 部長は
小惑星が来るって知っていて…
So you knew that the meteoroid was coming, and you still...
- Cut off their
transmission.
交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
こいつらの交信を切れ
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, お嬢[おじょう]:(someone else's) daughter, 責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability
お願いします
お嬢さんとのことは僕だけの責任に
Please, sir! What happened to your daughter
is my responsibility, no one else's!
I'll have to ask you to walk away
from this, Second Division.
そちら:that way (direction distant from the speaker, close to the listener)|there (place distant from the speaker, close to the listener), 手を引く[てをひく]:to withdraw from (a deal)/to wash one's hands of|to lead by the hand, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ノーマン）
そちらも手を引いてもらおうか
第２事業部君
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
はい！ ただいま
Yes, sir! At once, sir!
Hachi, come back here! That's an order
from the Third Division manager!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction
おい ハチ 戻ってこい
第３事業部長様の命令だ
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ハチマキ）
俺は 第２事業部だからな
I'm Second Division.
He's got no no authority over us.
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
関係ねえよ
平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 変わり[かわり]:change|unusual state or event|difference
平社員に変わりはない
But you're still a mere rank-and-file employee.
Are you going to disobey a superior?
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction, 逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey
上司命令に逆らうつもりか？
逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey
（ハチマキ）ああ 逆らうね
Damn right I am. This doesn't have anything
to do with who's labor and who's management.
平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
これは平とか上司とか
関係ないだろう！
衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
衝突まで あと２分25秒
Collision in two minutes, 25 seconds.
You little fool!
管轄[かんかつ]:jurisdiction/control, 平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 口答え[くちごたえ]:retort/back talk, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
バカもん うちの管轄では
平の口答えは禁止に決まっていて…
In my jurisdiction, rank-and-file employees
aren't allowed to backtalk their superiors!
（ハチマキ）うるせえ！
Shove it!
When somebody tells me something's
prohibited or tells me to stop something,
禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
俺はな 禁止とか
やめろって言われると―
かえって:on the contrary/rather/all the more, 性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
かえって
やりたくなる性格なんだよ！
...that makes we wanna
do it even more!
平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 分際[ぶんざい]:social standing, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful
平の分際で
何を偉そうに言ってる
How dare you talk to me
that way, you little peon!
（ハチマキ）な… ヤバッ
Oh, crap. It's got too much mass.
One Fishbone doesn't have the thrust to...
質量[しつりょう]:mass, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx, 推進力[すいしんりょく]:propulsive power/driving force
質量があり過ぎて
これ１台の推進力じゃ…
Senpai!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩！
（ハチマキ）おっ
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（タナベ）私も手伝います
I'll help!
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 慌てる[あわてる]:to become confused (disconcerted, disorganized, disorganised)/to be flustered|to be in a hurry
（ハチマキ）よーし 慌てんな
Okay, don't rush it. Stay calm and link up.
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, 連結[れんけつ]:concatenation/coupling/connection
落ち着いて 連結すりゃあいい
コピー:copy/photocopy
（タナベ）アイ コピー
I copy!
Avionics control
master-to-slave couplers, in.
アビオニクス:avionics, コントロール:control
（ハチマキ）
アビオニクス コントロール
マスター:to master/to learn, セーブ:save
マスタートゥーセーブ
コネクトイン
コネクト:connect, コンプリート:complete
（タナベ）コネクト コンプリート
Connection complete.
Okay, we'll do a de-orbit burn with our
combined thrusters. Punch it!
（ハチマキ）よし
連結[れんけつ]:concatenation/coupling/connection, 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 離脱[りだつ]:withdrawal/secession/separation, 一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer)
連結噴射で 軌道を離脱
一気に行くぞ！
コピー:copy/photocopy
（タナベ）アイ コピー
I copy!
Balancing remaining propellant.
Adjusting common center of gravity.
推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, 残量[ざんりょう]:remaining quantity/residual quantity, バランス:balance, 共通[きょうつう]:commonness|to be common|-wide, 重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination
（ハチマキ）推進剤 残量バランス
共通重心位置 調整
あいつら もう こうなったら―
- Composite vector now along axis of thrust.
Darn those two... All right, we'll just have
to cut off the module's location data feed...
モジュール:module, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, カット:cut/cutting
モジュールの
位置情報をカットして…
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
（ユーリ）
そこは船長以外 操作禁止です
No one but the captain is
allowed to touch the controls.
（ラビィ）お お… おい
ユーリ君 ちょ ちょっと
Hey! Yuri-kun, what do you
think you're doing?!
Hachimaki!
ハチマキ:headband, 合流[ごうりゅう]:confluence (of rivers)/merge (of traffic)|union (e.g. of forces), 座標[ざひょう]:coordinate/coordinates, ベクトル:vector, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
（フィー）ハチマキ 合流座標への
ベクトルを送るから―
I'm sending you the vector for the rendezvous
coordinates, so push 'em over there.
押し出し[おしだし]:pushing something out|presence|run walked in|
そこまで押し出しな
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
I copy.
This sector belongs to Third Division!
I'm the top dog around here!
宙[ちゅう]:space/air|(from) memory, 域[いき]:region/limits/stage, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ノーマン）
この宙域は 第３事業部のものだ
いちばん:number one/first|best, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
私が いちばん偉いんだぞ
聞こえてんのか？ おい
Are you listening to me?! Hey!
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
うるさい！
（ノーマン）なっ
Shove it!
If we don't do something here,
it's gonna create debris!
デブリ:debris
（フィー）このままじゃ
デブリができちまうんだよ
Do you expect us to sit back
and do nothing?! Do you?!
黙る[だまる]:to be silent
黙って見てろってのか ああ？
押す[おす]:to push|to apply pressure from above|to stamp (i.e. a passport)||
（ハチマキ）よし 押せ！
Okay, start pushing!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
はい 先輩
Right, Senpai!
Combustion at maximum. Continuing to
increase thrust and build up delta-V!
燃焼[ねんしょう]:burning/combustion, 最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest, 推力[すいりょく]:thrust/driving force/propulsion, 増加[ぞうか]:increase/rise/growth, 続行[ぞっこう]:continuation/continuance/going on
（ハチマキ）燃焼最大
推力増加 デルタブイ 増速続行
遷移[せんい]:transition, 軌道に乗る[きどうにのる]:to be on track/to be going to plan|to enter orbit, 同時[どうじ]:simultaneous/concurrent/same time, 燃焼[ねんしょう]:burning/combustion, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination
遷移軌道に乗ると同時に燃焼終了！
Will cut thrust once
transfer orbit reached!
セカンダリ:secondary, セパレート:separate
セカンダリ･ハル セパレート
Secondary hull,
separate.
Linkage joints, disengaged.
Laser guidance control, confirmed.
ジョイント:joint, 連結[れんけつ]:concatenation/coupling/connection, 解除[かいじょ]:cancellation/rescinding/release, レーザー:laser/Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation, レーザー:leather, 誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ジョイント連結 解除
レーザー誘導制御 確認
Separation complete.
セパレート:separate, コンプリート:complete, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 捕捉[ほそく]:capture/seizure|apprehension, 誘導[ゆうどう]:guidance/leading/induction, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking
セパレート コンプリート
対象捕捉 誘導制御
Target acquired.
Guidance control. Fine-tuning relative velocity
while in neutral position to target.
相対[あいたい]:confrontation/facing/between ourselves, 相対[そうたい]:relativity|relative, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, 中立[ちゅうりつ]:neutrality, 中立[なかだち]:break between the light meal and the actual serving of tea (during a formal tea ceremony), 姿勢[しせい]:attitude/posture/stance, 微[び]:minuteness|one millionth, 調整[ちょうせい]:adjustment/regulation/coordination, ランデブー:meeting/rendez-vous, コンプリート:complete
相対速度を中立姿勢のまま微調整
ランデブー コンプリート
Rendezvous complete. Vectors synchronized!
ベクター:vector, シンクロ:synchronization, キャッチアップ:catch-up
ベクターシンクロ キャッチアップ
Catch up.
Target secured. Ignition!
対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 確保[かくほ]:guarantee/maintain/ensure, イグニッション:ignition
対象を確保 イグニッション
Experiment module EM42
is exiting its orbit.
実験[じっけん]:experiment, モジュール:module, 周回[しゅうかい]:going around/orbiting|circumference, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 離脱[りだつ]:withdrawal/secession/separation
（社員）実験モジュール
EM-42 周回軌道を離脱します
Target meteoroid
will make a near miss.
対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 小惑星[しょうわくせい]:asteroid
対象小惑星はフライバイ
くうっ…
Put me through to Second Division.
I want to talk to their boss.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, つなげる:to tie/to fasten/to connect
第２事業部につなげ
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
やつらのボスと直接 話す
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩 あれ
（ハチマキ）ああっ？
Senpai, look!
つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
（ニン）つながっているんですか？
Do we have
a connection?
音声[おんせい, おんじょう]:voice/(the concept of) sound
（研究課長）
なんとか音声だけはな
Barely. It's voice-only.
It'll be enough.
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
（ニン）十分です
声[こえ]:voice, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
この声 さっきの
That's the man
from earlier!
うん
Section Division crew,
do you read me?
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
（ニン）
第２事業部デブリ課の皆さん
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえますか？
（ラビィ）ああっ 聞こえてますよ
Yes, we read you!
Thank you. Now we can go
to Mars with no regrets.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（ニン）ありがとう
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
これで私たちは
気持ちよく 火星に行けます
I see.
そうか
We've decided to continue
our work on Mars.
研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet), 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on, ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
（ニン）
研究は火星で続けることにします
実験[じっけん]:experiment, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit, 祈る[いのる]:to pray/to wish
（フィー）実験の成功を祈ってるよ
Well, I hope your experiments
are successful.
Oh, and give my best
to your girlfriend, too.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
ああ それから 彼女にも よろしく
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 火星[かせい]:Mars (planet)
連れてくって手もあるよなあ
火星に
You could always take her with you
to Mars, you know.
あっ…
コピー:copy/photocopy
あ… アイ コピー
I copy!
Thank you so much, Debris Section.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
本当に ありがとうございました
デブリ課の皆さん それでは
Over and out.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, にらむ:to glare at/to scowl at|to stare intensely at
（ラビィ）
ああ… 事業部長ににらまれる
The division manager's gonna have my hide...
What'll it be? Dismissal, demotion, a pay cut?
左遷[させん]:demotion/relegation/reduction in rank, 減俸[げんぽう]:salary reduction/salary cut
クビか 左遷か 減俸か
（フィー）フフッ どうかなあ
（ラビィ）へえ？
I wouldn't be
so sure.
フッ
If there's one thing that Dolf's always hated,
it's being ordered by someone to do something.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
ドルフって昔から嫌いなんだよな
あれこれ:one thing or another/this way and that|around
人から あれこれ言われるの
Hey, are you listening to me? Your people
acted improperly inside my jurisdiction!
（ノーマン）おい 聞いてるのか！
管轄[かんかつ]:jurisdiction/control, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, やらかす:to fail/to blunder|to drink up
私の管轄内で
勝手なことをやらかして
How do you intend to
make amends for this?
落とし前[おとしまえ]:money paid to settle a fight
この落とし前
どうつけるつもりなんだ
You have
my apologies.
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse
（ドルフ）申し訳ありません
However, they did what they did to
prevent the creation of debris, correct?
デブリ:debris, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny, 防ぐ[ふせぐ]:to defend against/to protect against|to prevent
しかし 彼らは
デブリの発生を防いだのでしょ？
They did what the Debris Section
is supposed to do.
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 当然[とうぜん]:natural/as a matter of course/justified, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
デブリ課としては当然の仕事かと
縄張り[なわばり]:stretching a rope around/roping off|one's turf, 荒らす[あらす]:to lay waste|to invade|to troll (e.g. web forums)
（ノーマン）何だと！
うちの縄張りを荒らしておいて
What did you say?!
They screwed things up inside my turf!
抗議[こうぎ]:protest/objection, 後ほど[のちほど]:later on/eventually/afterwards, 正式[せいしき]:due form/official/formality, 文書[ぶんしょ, もんじょ]:document/writing|document addressed to someone in particular (jargon used in paleography), 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（ドルフ）抗議でしたら 後ほど
正式な文書でお願いできますか？
If you'd like to lodge a complaint,
could you do it in an official document?
Make sure to include concrete examples of
how they breached company regulations.
社則[しゃそく]:company regulations, 抵触[ていしょく]:collision|being contrary|being in violation (of a law, treaty, etc.), 具体的[ぐたいてき]:concrete/tangible/definite
社則に どう抵触するのか具体的に
ああ…
新型[しんがた]:new type/new style/new model, ブリージング:breathing, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
さっすが 新型
ブリージングも早いな
These new ships sure run through
the breathing sequence fast.
Do you think we'll be okay?
We disobeyed a division manager.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey
大丈夫なんですかね
事業部長に逆らっちゃって
禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
俺は禁止とか
やめろって言われると―
When somebody tells me something's prohibited
or orders me to stop, it makes we want to do it.
やりたくなるんだよ
I bet Lavie-san is passed out
in the cockpit.
今頃[いまごろ]:about this time, コクピット:cockpit, 卒倒[そっとう]:fainting/swooning
今頃 コクピットで
ラビィさんが卒倒してますね
禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
だから俺は
禁止とか やめろって言われると…
Like I said, if somebody says
something is prohibited, l...
Right, right. You already said that.
はいはい
それは もう聞きましたよ
タナベ？
Tanabe...
Yes?
はい？
Office romances are
prohibited, right?
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 恋愛[れんあい]:love/love-making/passion, 禁止[きんし]:prohibition/inhibition/ban
社内恋愛って禁止なんだよな？
あ…
Tanabe, um... About you and me...
Do you want to...
タナベ その… 俺と…
...do it?
するか？
スケベ:lewdness/lewd person/lecher
な… 何言ってんですか？ スケベ
Wha...?! What're you saying,
you pervert?!
いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden
いきなりそんなこと言われて―
How could I possibly say yes if you ask me like that?!
イエス:Jesus, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
イエスって言えるわけ…
（ハチマキ）バ… バカ！
- M-Moron, I didn't
mean that!
意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
そういう意味じゃねえよ
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 続き[つづき]:sequel/continuation/(also suffix) continuation (in time and space)
この間の… 地球の続きを
するかってことで
I meant... picking up where
we left off on Earth.
I'm asking you if you want
to go out with me.
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other, 分かれる[わかれる]:to branch|to separate|to disperse
俺とつきあわないかって
言ってんだろ 分かれよ
Do I have to spell it out?!
分かりませんよ！
How am I supposed to know that?!
For one thing, you've
got no delicacy!
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, デリカシー:delicacy/tact/considerateness, 欠ける[かける]:to be chipped|to be lacking|to be insufficient|
大体 先輩は
デリカシーに欠けるんです
You go through other people's drawers
and you walk around in your diapers!
引き出し[ひきだし]:drawer|withdrawal|variety of knowledge and experience useful for handling things impromptu, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 歩く[あるく]:to walk
人の引き出しは勝手に開けるし
おむつのまま 外 歩くし
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
お前だってしてんだろ おむつ
Look who's talking! You wear diapers, too!
はっ…
デリカシー:delicacy/tact/considerateness, 欠ける[かける]:to be chipped|to be lacking|to be insufficient|
そういうところが
デリカシーに欠けるっていうんです
That's why I'm saying that
you've got no delicacy!
あ…
…で どうなんだよ
So, what's it gonna be?
えっ…
Your answer.
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response
（ハチマキ）返事
ああ…
ん…
ああっ…
ウフッ
（ハチマキ）あっ…
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
In her Case...
取り引き[とりひき]:transactions/dealings/business, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（ギガルト）
取り引き場所は―
The deal will be made here at Seven.
セブン:seven
このセブンだ
This trio came up here yesterday.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
昨日 ３人組が
上がってきている
午後[ごご]:afternoon/p.m., 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting), 頂ける[いただける]:to be able to receive|to be able to eat|to be acceptable
午後から お休みを
頂けませんか？
Would you mind if I took
the afternoon off?
（サーシャ）
君に会いに来たのさ
I came here
to see you.
（ハチマキ）
んっ… あ…
話せる[はなせる]:to be able to speak/to be able to talk|to be understanding
何か話せよ
Say something,
damn it.